Estefano Matías **Muñoz Moya**

🛘 (+56) 9 4567 1909 | 🗷 estefano.munoz@usach.cl | 🎢 estefano23.github.io | 🖸 0000-0001-5222-4071 | 🔞 Estefano-Munoz-Moya | 🔽 estefano23

Presentation_

Master's degree in Engineering Sciences, specialization in Mechanical Engineering, approved with the highest distinction. Researchers in biomechanics and biomaterials focused on experimental and numerical work, numerical methods, solid mechanics, finite element method, and continuum mechanics. Responsible, proactive, with excellent learning capacity, empathetic with others, tolerant to failure, and work under pressure.

Education _

University of Santiago de Chile (USACH)

MASTER DEGREE | AWARDED | HIGHEST DISTINCTION | GPA: 6.9/7.0

· M.Sc. Mechanical Engineering.

University of Santiago de Chile (USACH)

B.Sc. Degree | Awarded | GPA: 6.2/7.0

· Mechanical Engineering

Santiago, Chile

2018 - 2020

Santiago, Chile

Work Experience

University of Santiago de Chile (USACH), Department of Mechanical Engineering (DIMEC)

PART-TIME TEACHER: Engineering Drawing | THEORY. PART-TIME TEACHER: Strength of Materials | LABORATORY. PART-TIME TEACHER: Introduction to Mechanical Engineering | THEORY. PART-TIME TEACHER: Computational Mechanical Design | THEORY. PART-TIME TEACHER: Engineering Drawing | LABORATORY.

Centre for Climate Change Research and Innovation (CiiCC) | Santo Tomás University (UST)

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | PROJECT PIA-ANID ANILLO ACT 172037 | Ph. D. Nelson A. Lagos

Apr. 2021 - **PRESENT**

Santiago, Chile

Apr. 2021 - PRESENT Apr. 2021 - PRESENT

Oct. 2020 - Mar. 2021 Oct. 2020 - Mar. 2021

Santiago, Chile

- Oct. 2018 **PRESENT**
- Researcher assistant in the project: Interacting structure and function of ecological, mechanical and mineralogical properties of marine calcifiers: Shell carbonates as sources of bio-inspiration (Carbo-Nat-Lab).
- · Experimental and numerical computational research work on the shell skeleton structure from the Chilean coast.
- Mechanical studies on chillean mollusk shells, Perumytilus purpuratus, subjet to climate change scenarios.

Biomechanical and Biomaterials Laboratory (BioMatLab) | University of Santiago de Chile (USACH)

Santiago, Chile

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | PROJECT FONDECYT 1170608F | Ph. D. CLAUDIO M. GARCÍA-HERRERA | Ph. D. DIEGO J. CELENTANO

- Oct. 2018 **PRESENT**
- Researcher assistant in the project: Biomechanical Behaviour of Arteries from Chronic Hypoxic Animals: Experiments, Modelling, Numerical Simulation and Validation.
- · Mechanical studies in arteries in collaboration with the veterinary medical center of the University of Chile.
- Biomechanical characterization of arteries to observe adverse effects, such as hypoxia suffered by Chilean mining workers.
- Perform ROT (Ring Opening Test) on arteries to assess residual stresses.

University of Santiago de Chile (USACH), Department of Mechanical Engineering (DIMEC)

TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Introduction to Mechanical Engineering.

TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Strength of Materials. TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Applied Mathematics.

TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Thermal Systems (Thermodynamics II).

• Teaching assistance and development of educational guides/tests and resources.

Santiago, Chile

Mar. 2020 - Sep. 2020 Mar. 2019 - Aug. 2019

Aug. 2018 - Aug. 2019

Jul. 2017 - Jan. 2019

BBVA Bank Santiago, Chile

PROFESSIONAL PRACTICE IN THE FIELD OF TRIBOLOGICAL MAINTENANCE.

· Maintenance of buildings and power generators of the bank.

Jan. 2017 - Feb. 2017

Publications | Accepted / Under Review / In Progress

UNDER REVIEW | MATERIALS SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING: C

First Author | 2021

• Estefano Muñoz-Moya, Claudio M. García-Herrera, Nelson A. Lagos, Aldo Abarca-Ortega, Antonio G. Checa. Biomechanical behavior of the Perumytilus purpuratus shell: symmetry, homogeneity, and remodeling of the mechanical properties. Materials Science and Engineering: C. 2021.

UNDER REVIEW | PLOS ONE Second Author | 2021

 Aldo Abarca-Ortega, Estefano Muñoz-Moya, Matías Pacheco-Alarcón, Claudio M. García-Herrera, Diego J. Celentano, Nelson A. Lagos, Marco A. Lardies. Biomechanical characterization of scallop shells exposed to ocean acidification and warming. PLoS ONE. 2021.

In Progress First Author | 2021

• Estefano Muñoz-Moya, Matías Pacheco-Alarcón, Claudio M. García-Herrera, Aldo Abarca-Ortega, Nelson A. Lagos, Antonio G. Checa. Numerical simulation of Perumytilus purpuratus shell strength under predation attacks using finite element analysis. 2021.

Conferences

11° World Biomaterials Congress (WBC 2020), International Union of Societies for Biomaterials **Science and Engineering**

Europe, Virtual

International | Poster Presentation | Certificate Link | Poster Link

Dec. 2020

· MECHANICAL BEHAVIOR SYMMETRY OF MUSSEL SHELLS AND NUMERICAL METHOD FOR BIOMATERIAL ORTHOTROPY DIRECTIONS.

2° Congreso de Estudiantes de Postgrado USACH (USACH 2020), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

USACH, Virtual

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov. 2020

PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS: SIMETRÍA DE VALVAS Y CARACTERIZACIÓN DE DIRECCIÓN ORTÓTROPA.

Congreso Chileno de Biomecánica y Biomateriales (CBIO 2020), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

USACH, Virtual

Oct 2020

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | ORGANIZER | CERTIFICATE LINK

PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS: SIMETRÍA DE VALVAS Y CARACTERIZACIÓN DE DIRECCIÓN ORTÓTROPA.

19° Congreso Internacional de Metalurgia y Materiales (CONAMET-SAM 2019), Universidad Austral de Chile.

UACH, Valdivia, Chile

INTERNATIONAL | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov. 2019

ANÁLISIS DE LA RESPUESTA BIOMECÁNICA DE PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS ANTE ESCENARIOS DE CAMBIO CLIMÁTICO.

1° Congreso de Estudiantes de Postgrado USACH (USACH 2019), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

USACH. Santiago, Chile

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Aug. 2019

MODELOS CONSTITUTIVOS DE CRECIMIENTO APLICADOS A LA CONCHA DEL PERUMYTILUS PUPURATUS.

25° Congress of the European Society of Biomechanics (ESB 2019), Vienna University of

Technology.

TU Wien, Vienna, Austria

INTERNATIONAL | 2 SPEAKER PRESENTATIONS | CERTIFICATE LINK

Jul. 2019

- BIOMECHANICAL BEHAVIOUR ON SHELL CHARACTERISTICS (PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS) ALONG THE CHILEAN COAST.
- NUMERICAL ANALYSIS OF THE BIOMECHANICAL RESPONSE OF OYSTER SHELLS SUBJECTED TO CLIMATE CHANGE SCENARIOS.

Courses

English as a Medium of Instruction (EMI) - Content and Language Integrated Learning (CLIL)

Dalhousie University, Virtual

PEDAGOGIC TRAINING PROGRAM | STUDENT

Apr. 2021 - **PRESENT**

· Dictated by the Department of International and Inter-University Relations (DRII-USACH), and the Academic Vice-Rectory (VRA-USACH) of the University of Santiago de Chile, with experts from Dalhousie University (Dal).

Structure, form, and function of calcifying organisms

CIMARQ UNAB, Valparaíso, Chile

POSTGRADUATE COURSE | STUDENT | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov. 2018

• Dictated by the academics Ph. D. Antonio Checa (University of Granada, Spain) and Ph. D. Fabio Labra (Santo Tomás University, Chile).

Memberships

European Society of Biomechanics (ESB)

Europe

STUDENT MEMBER | CERTIFICATE LINK

Jul. 2020 - **PRESENT**

• Membership ID: 3263

STEM Preeschoolar USACH-DIMEC (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics)

Santiago, Chile

MEMBER | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2019 - **PRESENT**

Scientific popularization for preschool children with a gender perspective.

Science Popularization

Science Festival - Festival de la Ciencia (FECI of PAR Explora Región Metropolitana Sur Poniente, ANID), Universidad de Chile

UCHILE, Virtual

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

• Science experiments for children.

Nov. 2020

Science Festival - 10° Feria Científica USACH, Universidad de Santiago de Chile

USACH, Santiago, Chile

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2019

· Exhibition of biomechanical tests for children.

Exhibition - *Molluscas*, *espiral del cambio* of the CarboNatLab project - Ci*i*CC, Museo de Historia Natural de Valparaíso (MHNV)

MHNV, Valparaíso, Chile

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

• Exhibition of the consequences of climate change in the oceans.

Oct. 2019

Exhibition - XII Fiesta de la ciencia y la tecnología (PAR Explora Región Metropolitana Sur Oriente, ANID ex CONICYT), Universidad de Chile

PARQUEMET, Santiago, Chile

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2018

• Exhibition of the mechanical properties of the mollusk shells subject to climate change scenarios.

About me_

Full name: Estefano Matías Muñoz Mova

BASIC INFORMATION

- Chilean RUT: 19.001.917-9 | Passport: F27796026
- Address: Paseo Pie Andino 2798, G44, Santiago, Chile
- Birth: 23th of September of 1994 | Age: 26 years old
- Birth place: Santiago, RM, Republic of Chile
- email: estefano.munoz@usach.cl
- · Lenguages: Native Spanish | Advanced English

PROGRAMMING LENGUAGES AND SOFTWARE USAGE

- Programming lenguages: : Fortran | Python | Matlab/Octave | C/C++ | HTML |
- Software usage: In-House Softwares | AutoCAD | Solidworks | Ansys | Inventor | Mathcad | Fusion360 | SAM | Latex | Arduino | Ubuntu | EDEM | GiD | InVesalius | Office (Word, PowerPoint, Excel, Project) |

References_

Ph. D. Claudio M. García-Herrera | ResearchGate Link, Director of the Mechanical Engineering Department, Associated Professor, and Researcher - University of Santiago de Chile (USACH). email: claudio.garcia@usach.cl

Ph. D. Nelson A. Lagos | ResearchGate Link, Director of the Centre for Climate Change Research and Innovation (Cii/CC), Associated Professor, and Researcher - Santo Tomás University (UST). email: nlagoss@santotomas.cl

Ph. D. Diego J. Celentano | ResearchGate Link, Associated Professor and Researcher of Mechanical and Metallurgical Engineering Department, Pontifical Catholic University of Chile (PUC Chile). email: dcelentano@ing.puc.cl